Guide to the Wayland Wells Williams Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Wayland Wells Williams papers
1910-1942
YCAL MSS 551
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.5
(6 boxes)
The collection contains drafts of writings and correspondence documenting the professional life of New Haven area writer Wayland Wells Williams. Writings contain drafts of published and unpublished novels, including Goshen Street (1920) and "The King of Iceland's Eldest Son," and shorter works. Correspondence includes letters from Yale professor William Lyon Phelps and from prominent contemporaries Thomas Beers and Monty Woolley. There are also production files relating to the collection of poems, Castle in Spain (1942), and a folder of condolence letters.
Williams, Wayland Wells, 1888-1945
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of D. V. Garstin, 1949-1950.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Samuel Wells Williams Family Papers (MS 547). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Wayland Wells Williams (1888-1945)
Wayland Wells Williams, New Haven author and artist, was the son of Frederick Wells and Fanny Hapgood, a graduate of Yale University, and administrator of the Connecticut Federal Art Project.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains drafts of writings and correspondence documenting the professional life of New Haven area writer Wayland Wells Williams. Writings contain drafts of published and unpublished novels, including Goshen Street (1920) and "The King of Iceland's Eldest Son," and shorter works. Correspondence includes letters from Yale professor William Lyon Phelps and from prominent contemporaries Thomas Beers and Monty Woolley. There are also production files relating to the collection of poems, Castle in Spain (1942), and a folder of condolence letters.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1919-1940. II. Correspondence, 1910-1942.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Beer, Thomas, 1889-1940; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943; Williams, Wayland Wells, 1888-1945; Woolley, Monty, 1888-1963
- Writings, 1919-1940; Series I; 2.3; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Writings contains drafts for published and unpublished novels and shorter works, including plays and stories.
  - "Aesthetics of the Human Figure," essay, draft, typescript, undated (Box 1)
  - "Aminta," play, draft, typescript carbon and autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
  - Castle in Spain, poems, drafts, typescript, corrected, 1939, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "The Cid," play, draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Crambler Emerald," story, draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
  - Family, novel, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, [circa 1923]; 2 (Box 1)
  - "A Game of Bridge," story, draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
  - Goshen Street, novel, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, 1919; 2 (Box 2)
  - I, The King, novel, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - "The King of Iceland's Eldest Son," novel, drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - "Lavinia," drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript carbon, corrected, 1924, undated; 6 (Box 3)
  - "Matthew," novel, draft, typescript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - "Mrs. Maddon," draft, autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Notes on an Observation of Physical Types..." drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected, and typescript carbon, 1940, undated (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence with William Sheldon
  - "Opus 1," play, draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4)
  - "Savonarola Brown," play, draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 4)
  - "Second Choice," play, drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected, and typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Second Choice," play, drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected, and typescript carbon, undated; 4 (Box 5)
  - "Slopes," story, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 5)
  - "The Slush Slinger," story, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, 1926 (Box 5)
  - "The Woodchuck's Back Door," story, draft, autograph manuscript and typescript carbon, corrected, 1922; 2 (Box 5)
  - "The Wren," story, draft, typescript, undated (Box 5)
  - Untitled play, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 5)
  - Untitled play, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 6)
  - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 6)
- Correspondence, 1910-1942; Series II; 7
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  Series II. Correspondence contains letters from Yale professor William Lyon Phelps and from Williams's contemporaries Thomas Beers and Monty Woolley. There are also production files relating to the collection of poems, Castle in Spain, and a folder of condolence letters.
  - Beer, Thomas, 1915-1929, undated (Box 6)
    Includes photograph
  - Phelps, William Lyon, 1910-1937 (Box 6)
    Includes photographs
  - Woolley, Monty, 1917-1919, undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence relating to Castle in Spain, 1940-1942, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - Sympathy letters on the death of Williams's father, 1928, undated (Box 6)
  - Other correspondents, 1916-1939 (Box 6)